Did you ever wonder if certain foods
have a direct effect on your health?
Well, I’m here to
solve that mystery
since you are
the foods you eat.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we bring you new research
about prostate cancer
and we start with the sometimes
problematic results of PSA testing.
While 64 percent of men
develop hidden prostate cancers
by their 60s,
the lifetime risk of being
diagnosed with prostate cancer
is only about 11 percent,
and the risk of dying from
prostate cancer, 2.5 percent,
at the average age of 80.
So most men develop
prostate cancer
but they die with their tumors
rather than from their tumors.
Most men with prostate cancer
live their whole lives
never knowing they even had it.
That's one of the problems
screening for it.
Many prostate cancers
that are detected
may never have led to harm
even if they'd gone
undiscovered.
Nonetheless,
not all men are so lucky.
About 30,000 Americans die
each year from prostate cancer.
So, should you get a PSA
prostate screening test or not?
PSA stands for
prostate specific antigen,
an enzyme secreted
by cells of the prostate
to liquefy semen
and cervical mucus
to facilitate fertilization.
Elevated levels in the blood can
be a sign of prostate cancer,
which led to FDA approval
as a screening test
for the early detection
of prostate cancer in the 1990s.
If it comes back high,
the test is usually repeated.
If it's still high,
the next step is typically
an ultrasound-guided
biopsy of the prostate
through the rectum.
If there's cancer,
then options include surgery,
radiation, and chemotherapy,
or a delayal of treatment.
However the USPSTF,
the US Preventive Services
Task Force,
the main independent
scientific panel
that sets evidence-based
clinical prevention guidelines,
recommended against
routine PSA screening,
as does the American College
of Preventive Medicine,
the American Academy
of Family Physicians,
and the vast majority,
85 percent of professional
medical societies
in developed countries
around the world, opposed.
In 2018, though,
the USPSTF shifted from
a summary judgement against
to, quote, "the decision about
whether to be screened
for prostate cancer should
be an individual one," unquote,
which is more in line with the
"shared decision making" stance
of the American
Urological Association,
the American College
of Physicians,
and the American Cancer Society.
In other words,
men should be informed
about the risks and benefits
and decide for themselves.
However,
men who are on the fence
and don't express
a clear preference
in favor of screening
should not be screened,
according to the latest
USPSTF recommendations.
More recently, an international
panel of experts concluded
that clinicians
need not feel obligated
to systematically bring it up,
judging that most men would
decide to decline PSA testing,
given the clear harms and
small and uncertain benefits.
That, however, is up to you.
I personally declined,
but let's run the numbers.
Similar to the 92 percent
of women who didn't know
or overestimated the mortality
reduction from mammograms
by tenfold or more,
89 percent of men vastly
overestimated the benefits
of prostate cancer screening
or simply had no idea.
Most thought 50 prostate cancer
deaths could be prevented
out of a thousand men
regularly screened,
when in reality,
it's more like one.
But doesn't even a 1-in-1,000
chance of not dying from cancer
make a few blood tests worth it?
The downsides are more
than inconvenience, though.
About one in seven men
who undergo PSA screening
will test positive,
yet in two-thirds of the cases,
the biopsy results
will be normal.
So out of the thousand men
regularly screened,
about 150 will have
a false alarm
and be biopsied unnecessarily,
which can cause
minor complications
like pain and bloody ejaculate,
or in approximately
1 percent of cases,
more serious complications,
like blood-borne infections
that require hospitalization.
The greatest harm, though,
is overdiagnosis.
Unnecessary biopsies
are bad enough,
but nothing, compared to
unnecessary cancer treatment.
Large-scale randomized trials
suggest that
20 to 50 percent of men
diagnosed with prostate cancer
would have never become
symptomatic in their lifetime.
They never would
have been any wiser
had they not been screened,
but now they may be needlessly
heading to the operating table.
About 3 in 1,000 men die
during or soon after
radical prostatectomy.
That may help explain
why there appears to be
no overall mortality benefit
to prostate cancer screening.
For every life that is saved,
another may be extinguished
for a cancer
they never would have even
known about.
Another 50 in 1,000 men
end up with serious
surgical complications.
Even if the surgery
goes smoothly,
about one in five men develop
long-term urinary incontinence
requiring the use of pads,
and most men--
two out of three--
will experience long-term
erectile dysfunction.
Most men who receive
radiation therapy
also experience long-term
sexual erectile dysfunction
and up to one in six experience
long-term bowel issues
such as fecal incontinence.
If this was saving your life,
it would be worth it,
but over 16 years,
rather than being saved
from a prostate cancer death
by screening,
it may be 25 times more likely
that you were instead
overdiagnosed with a cancer
that wouldn't have bothered you.
Yet you come away
after treatment
thinking the PSA test
saved your life.
It's like with the mammograms.
The people who are
harmed the most--
unnecessary cancer treatment--
feel as though
they've been helped the most.
In our next story,
we look at a novel approach
to help men change their diet
after a prostate cancer diagnosis.
A cancer diagnosis is seen
as a teachable moment in medicine
where we can try to get
people to eat healthier,
but research suggests that
male cancer patients in particular
may be reluctant to
introduce dietary modifications.
This has been attributed
to dietary changes
often being viewed as mimicking
“feminine” eating behaviors,
such as emphasizing an
increase in fruit and vegetables.
Although healthy eating
might enhance long-term survival,
few men with prostate cancer
make dietary changes
to advance their
well-being.
Many of the cancer
survival trials for example,
required adherence to strict,
plant-based diets,
and though researchers tried
providing extensive nutrition
education and counseling
programs,
dietary adherence was
still a challenge.
The way Dean Ornish
was apparently able to reverse
the progression of prostate
cancer with a plant-based diet
was home delivering prepared
meals to their door,
figuring men
are so lazy
they'll just eat whatever's
put in front of them.
After all, male culture tends
to encourage men to go for
convenience food,
meat, and beer.
Take Men’s Health
magazine, for example.
Included in their
list of things
men should never
apologize for:
liking McDonald’s, not offering
a vegetarian alternative,
and laughing at people
who eat trail mix.
It featured articles
with titles like,
“Vegetables Are for Girls,”
and sections like
“Men and Meat: There’s Only One
Kind of Flesh We Like Better,
and Even Then, She’d Better
Know How to Grill!”
To appeal to male
sensibilities,
doctors are advised to use
‘body as machine’ metaphors,
framing men’s health in
terms of mechanical objects,
such as cars
requiring tuning.
But if men are so concerned
about their masculinity and manhood,
maybe we should instead
share a bit about
what prostate cancer
treatment entails.
The prostate is situated at
the base of the penis,
and so when you
core it out
with a radical
prostatectomy,
you lose about an inch
off your penis,
IF... it gets
erect at all.
Only 16% of men
undergoing the procedure
will regain their
pre-surgery level
of erectile functioning.
Patients are typically quoted
erectile dysfunction rates
around 60% or 70%,
but studies have generally
considered erectile function recovery
as just the ability to
maintain an erection
hard enough for
penetration
about 50% of the time.
So getting it up occasionally
is considered recovery.
But when a surgeon tells a patient
he will recover function,
the patient probably assumes
that means the kind of function
they had prior
to surgery.
And that only happens
16% of the time,
and only 4% of the time
in men over 60.
Only 1 in 25 get their baseline
sexual function back.
And it’s not
just erections,
but other problems like OAP,
orgasm-associated pain
even years later,
and urinary incontinence
during foreplay,
stimulation, or orgasm.
The vast majority of
couples overestimate
how much function
they’re going to recover.
Couples reported feeling
loss and grief.
Having cancer
is bad enough
without the
additional losses.
You’d think that
would be enough
to motivate men to
improve their diets,
but almost a fourth
of men newly diagnosed
with prostate cancer state
that they would prefer
to have their lives cut
short rather than living
with a diet that prohibits
beef and pork.
More men would
rather be impotent
than improve
their diet.
It appears pleasures
of the flesh
may sometimes
even trump…
pleasures of the flesh.
In our final story today,
cranberries and pumpkin
seeds are put to the test
for benign prostatic hypertrophy.
More than 50% of men in their 50's
and 70% or more of men in their 60's
suffer from benign prostatic
hypertrophy or BPH,
otherwise known
as enlarged prostate.
This can result in burdensome
lower urinary tract symptoms
such as having to get up
frequently at night to pee.
Current medical treatments are
clinically effective, but their efficacy
is compromised by side effects
and low compliance rates.
Symptoms include sexual dysfunction,
high-grade prostate cancer,
and depression. No wonder
there's poor compliance.
And when medication treatment fails,
surgical procedures are considered,
such as transurethral
resection of the prostate.
There has got to be a better way.
Population studies suggest
that low intake of animal protein
and high intake of fruits and
vegetables may be protective,
but not just cutting down
on any animal protein.
Eggs and poultry seem to be the
worst, along with refined grains,
but no association was found
for red meat or dairy.
Population studies aside, are there any
foods that have been put to the test?
There have been more than 30
randomized controlled trials
on the herb saw palmetto, and it's
been found to be totally useless.
Evidently, cranberries were used
by Native Americans to treat
urinary ailments, but you don't
know until you put 'em to the test.
Now, when they say dried cranberries,
they're not talking about those sugary,
oily craisins, but rather just
straight, whole cranberry powder.
And significant improvements were
seen in BPH symptoms, quality of life,
and all urination parameters
for just about a teaspoon a day
of powdered cranberries.
So we know a teaspoon works,
but what about a third of a teaspoon
or a sixth of a teaspoon?
They also helped.
So, you might as well buy it
in bulk for much cheaper
and just add it to a
smoothie or something.
What about using a berry
that's a little tastier,
like drinking purple grape juice?
No benefit whatsoever.
In a previous video, I talked
about the use of flaxseeds,
which may have a therapeutic
efficacy comparable to that
of commonly used drugs,
with only good side effects.
Okay, so what about other seeds?
Pumpkin seeds have evidently
been used in folk medicine
as a remedy for prostate
disorders for centuries,
and in a petri dish, they can cut the
growth of BPH prostate cells in half.
Scientists have also injected
pumpkin seed extracts into rabbits,
but what about people?
Pumpkin seed oil appears
to help with prostate issues.
When pitted head-to-head
against the drug Prazosin,
it seemed to work
as well as the pill.
The same when it was head-to-head
against the drug Terazosin.
What they didn't have though
was a placebo group.
It would have been nice to see how
well the pumpkin seed oil supplements
did against placebo, and hey,
in an ideal world, I'd love to also see
a group just given whole
pumpkin seeds themselves,
and boom: there it is. More than
a thousand men were randomized
to either a pumpkin seed
extract, a placebo,
or just about a tablespoon
a day of plain pumpkin seeds.
The study was funded by the drug
company that made the supplement,
but the supplement flopped,
it was no better than placebo,
but the pumpkin seeds
themselves worked.
The supplement appeared to reduce
symptoms, but not better than placebo.
However, just the plain old seeds did.
So it wasn't just some compound
extracted from the oil.
And, in fact, we've since learned that
even an oil-free extract seemed to work.
Bottom line, the researchers concluded,
is that pumpkin seed could be
recommended for BPH patients
with mild-to-moderate symptoms.
This conclusion was echoed by the
European equivalent of the FDA.
Pumpkin seeds can be used for the
relief of lower urinary tract symptoms
related to an enlarged prostate
after more serious conditions
have been excluded
by a medical doctor.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.